<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss  xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" 
      xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" 
      xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" 
      xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" 
      version="2.0">
<channel>
<title>Dr. Jorge Abreu Vicente</title>
<link>https://drabreu.github.io/web/featured_research.html</link>
<atom:link href="https://drabreu.github.io/web/featured_research.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
<description></description>
<generator>quarto-1.3.450</generator>
<lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
<item>
  <title>Galactic Paleontology: Unraveling the cosmic web of the Galaxy</title>
  <dc:creator>Dr. Jorge Abreu-Vicente</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Based on <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2016">(Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2016)</span>. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/es/posts/2023-11-02-filamentos-moleculares-gigantes/">Versión del post en español 🇪🇸</a>.</p>
<p>Science outreach of this work and authored by me was published and mentioned in the cover page of the <a href="https://www.globalastronomia.com/producto/astronomia-marzo-2022-no273-pdf/">March 2022 edition of the Astronomía Magazine</a> (only in Spanish).</p>
<section id="herschel-reveals-that-filaments-are-prevalent-in-molecular-clouds-and-preferred-sites-of-star-formation" class="level1">
<h1><em>Herschel</em> Reveals that Filaments are Prevalent in Molecular Clouds and Preferred Sites of Star Formation</h1>
<p>The field of star formation has recently experienced a rejuvenation thanks to infrared observations with the <em>Herschel</em> and <em>Spitzer</em> space telescopes. Until their launch, astronomers already knew that stars form in the densest and coldest zones of the Universe: the molecular clouds <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal">(Jorge Abreu-Vicente 2023)</span>. However, <em>Herschel</em> provided a new and more detailed view of this fact.</p>
<p><em>Herschel</em> revealed that stars primarily form inside filamentary structures within molecular clouds. The typical dimensions of these filaments are lengths of between 1 and 30 light-years and masses about 1000 times that of our Sun (these filaments could potentially create several hundred stars like ours). With this revelation, it became clear that filaments are a key part of star formation and the evolution of molecular clouds where it takes place.</p>
<div id="fig-protostars-in-filaments" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/protostars-in-filaments.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Forming stars within a filament in Orion."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;1: Infrared images obtained at Kitt Peak National Observatory (left) and with the Spitzer Space Telescope (NASA) of a young protostar in the Orion star-forming region. The dark filaments in the center of the image contain red sources that are generated by forming stars. The panel showing HOPS 383 demonstrates the variable emission of this protostar. This behavior is predicted by star formation theories. Image and source: E. Safron et al.; Background: NASA/JPL-Caltech/Univ. of Toledo)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="nessie-challenges-our-understanding-of-the-interstellar-medium" class="level1">
<h1><em>Nessie</em> Challenges Our Understanding of the Interstellar Medium</h1>
<p>A filamentary structure, nicknamed <em>Nessie</em> <span class="citation" data-cites="nessie">(Jackson et&nbsp;al. 2010)</span>, has been recently discovered with a length of 240 light-years and a total mass of 42,000 suns! This discovery has left astronomers astonished due to its clear deviation from other known filamentary structures to date. However, it has impacted the theoretical astrophysics community even more. According to current theories on star formation and the structure of molecular clouds, a filament of such magnitude should collapse gravitationally along its longitudinal axis so rapidly that its observation should not be possible.</p>
<div id="fig-nessie" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/nessie.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Nessie Filament."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;2: The Nessie filament appears in this image as a black serpentine against the green background of the infrared image from the <em>Spitzer</em> Space Telescope.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The questions arise naturally: are the observations mistaken? Perhaps we should revise our star formation theories? Is <em>Nessie</em> a special case, or could we find more such structures in our galaxy if we search for them? An interesting characteristic of Nessie is that observations show it to be part of one of the spiral arms of the Milky Way. If there is a network of similar filaments, and given that stars form in filaments, could we be on the verge of answering the elusive question of how stars form in the galactic context? In other words, what processes drive star formation at galactic scales? This article is directed towards the first necessary step to answer all these questions. Scouring the Milky Way for structures similar to Nessie.</p>
</section>
<section id="the-first-galactic-census-of-giant-filaments" class="level1">
<h1>The First Galactic Census of Giant Filaments</h1>
<p>In the article, we showcase the discovery of another 16 structures similar to Nessie (This post is for dissemination purposes. For details on how these structures were discovered, see <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2016">(Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2016)</span>). Therefore, we demonstrate that <em>Nessie</em> is not alone in this universe. The structures revealed by our work have sizes of up to 500 light-years and contain the mass of up to 100,000 suns like ours. However, our work shows that these structures are not found only in spiral arms, but can also appear in regions not associated with spiral arms.</p>
<div id="fig-distribucion-filamentos" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/filaments-in-galaxy.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Distribution of giant filaments in the Milky Way."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;3: Distribution of the giant filaments discovered to date of the article’s publication, placed over a theoretical/empirical scheme of the distribution of spiral arms of the Milky Way. Black filaments belong to our work, while the green is Nessie, and other colors belong to other filaments found by other works and methods. We refer to the article for references to the other works.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>These results raise another clear question: are there fundamental differences in the properties of giant filaments depending on whether they are in spiral arms or not? Our calculations clearly show that giant filaments associated with spiral arms have much greater potential for star formation. In other words, filaments in the arms have higher masses concentrated at high density. To understand this statement, read <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal">(Jorge Abreu-Vicente 2023)</span> where we show the direct relationship between dense gas and star-forming capacity.</p>
<p>So far, we have focused on the Milky Way. However, being part of it, our view is not as direct as it could be if we could observe the Galaxy from its zenith. Since we cannot do this for technical reasons, let’s see what we find in other galaxies, and if the observations corroborate our results in the Milky Way. In the PAWS project <span class="citation" data-cites="paws">(Schinnerer et&nbsp;al. 2013)</span>, detailed observations of the molecular clouds of galaxy M51 have been made (Figura&nbsp;4). In them, countless filamentary structures similar to <em>Nessie</em> and our giant filaments can be observed. After carrying out a series of calculations with their data, the results suggest that the trend towards greater star-forming potential in the spiral arm filaments is maintained in nearby galaxies (at least in M51).</p>
<p>It is now in the hands of the scientific community to move forward with these results and generate new observations to finally unveil the secret of star formation at the galactic scale. And, by extension, the evolution of molecular clouds at the scale of entire galaxies. Unfortunately, the necessary observations require levels of detail and sharpness that are probably only accessible to telescopes like ALMA. And this presents a series of challenges that suggest our search will need at least a decade to come to fruition.</p>
<div id="fig-paws" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/m51-paws.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Galaxy M51 observed by the PAWS project."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;4: The molecular clouds of galaxy M51 are shown in blue: the material necessary for the formation of new stars. Molecular emission was measured with the IRAM 30m telescope. Source: PAWS Team/IRAM/NASA HST/T. A. Rector (University of Alaska Anchorage)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>

<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Referencias</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_2016" class="csl-entry">
Abreu-Vicente, J., S. Ragan, J. Kainulainen, Th. Henning, H. Beuther, y K. Johnston. 2016. <span>«Giant molecular filaments in the Milky Way»</span>. <em>Astronomy <span>&amp;</span> Astrophysics</em> 590 (mayo): A131. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201527674">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201527674</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-nessie" class="csl-entry">
Jackson, James M., Susanna C. Finn, Edward T. Chambers, Jill M. Rathborne, y Robert Simon. 2010. <span>«<span>The <span>“Nessie”</span> Nebula: Cluster Formation in a Filamentary Infrared Dark Cloud</span>»</span> 719 (2): L185-89. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2041-8205/719/2/L185">https://doi.org/10.1088/2041-8205/719/2/L185</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal" class="csl-entry">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>«Revelando el causante de la formación estelar»</span>. 31 de octubre de 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-10-31-revelando-causa-formacion-estelar/">https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-10-31-revelando-causa-formacion-estelar/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-paws" class="csl-entry">
Schinnerer, Eva, Sharon E. Meidt, Jérôme Pety, Annie Hughes, Dario Colombo, Santiago Garcı́a-Burillo, Karl F. Schuster, et&nbsp;al. 2013. <span>«<span>The PdBI Arcsecond Whirlpool Survey (PAWS). I. A Cloud-scale/Multi-wavelength View of the Interstellar Medium in a Grand-design Spiral Galaxy</span>»</span> 779 (1): 42. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/779/1/42">https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/779/1/42</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Cómo citar</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{jorge abreu-vicente2023,
  author = {Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr.},
  title = {Galactic Paleontology: Unraveling the cosmic web of the
    Galaxy},
  date = {2023-11-02},
  url = {https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/},
  langid = {es}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">Por favor, cita este trabajo como:</div><div id="ref-jorge abreu-vicente2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>“Galactic Paleontology: Unraveling
the cosmic web of the Galaxy.”</span> November 2, 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/">https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Science</category>
  <category>Astronomy</category>
  <category>Star Formation</category>
  <category>PhD Thesis</category>
  <guid>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-02-giant-molecular-filaments/nessie.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="49" width="144"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Goolgles for Planck and Herschel. Enhanced calibration of Herschel and Planck Data in the Galactic plane</title>
  <dc:creator>Dr. Jorge Abreu-Vicente</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Based on <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2017">(Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2017)</span>. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/es/posts/2023-11-01-mejor-imagen-via-lactea-infrarrojo/">Versión del post en español 🇪🇸</a></p>
<section id="molecular-clouds-and-the-processes-inducing-star-formation" class="level1">
<h1>Molecular Clouds and the Processes Inducing Star Formation</h1>
<p>Stars are born in the densest and coldest regions of the interstellar medium (ISM), within vast agglomerations of molecules and dust known as molecular clouds <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal">(more information at Jorge Abreu-Vicente 2023)</span>. Due to their cold temperatures of about -250 degrees Celsius, molecular clouds do not emit in the optical range, appearing as black patches against the starry background in visible range images<sup>1</sup>. The light emitted by molecular clouds has a wavelength of between 60 and 1000 microns, about 100 times longer than the frequencies to which our eyes (between 0.4 and 0.7 microns) or optical telescopes like amateur ones are sensitive.</p>
<p>Far-infrared (FIR) astronomy is impossible from the ground, as our atmosphere blocks such radiation. Only the use of space telescopes like <em>Herschel</em> or <em>Planck</em> can allow for to the study of molecular clouds and the secrets of star formation physics.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-note callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Nota
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Molecular clouds also emit in sub- and millimeter waves, which are observable with ground-based radio telescopes like the IRAM 30m Telescope at Sierra Nevada, Spain. In fact, we need the combination of space and ground observations to study molecular clouds in their entirety.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>As shown in <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal">(Jorge Abreu-Vicente 2023)</span>, there is a direct relationship between the distribution of gas and dust in a molecular cloud and its star-forming activity. Specifically, molecular clouds with higher amounts of high-density gas form more stars than molecular clouds with low-density gas. In this project, we also comment that the current paradigm of the physical processes causing star formation has two main candidates: gravity and turbulence<sup>2</sup>. Although this work seems to decide for gravity, more direct and greater evidence is necessary for such a statement. The problem is that distinguishing between gravity and turbulence requires very precise measurements of the density or mass of molecular clouds.</p>
<p>This is one of the main scientific objectives of the launch of the European Space Agency (ESA) <em>Herschel</em> Space Observatory. The method used by <em>Herschel</em> to measure the density of molecular clouds is as follows. Molecular clouds emit following the <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ley_de_Planck">Planck’s Law</a>. This means that the molecular cloud emits as a body in thermodynamic equilibrium and therefore its emission is determined by its temperature and density. The emissions of molecular clouds as a function of the emitted wavelength can be observed in Figura&nbsp;1. In this figure, 5 vertical shadows are observed, corresponding to the wavelengths to which <em>Herschel</em> is sensitive. For each of the curves, the wavelength at which the maximum emission occurs is determined by the temperature of the molecular cloud. Also, the value of this maximum on the vertical axis is related to the observed gas density. The higher the gas density, the greater the emission. Thus, knowing the empirical function of Planck’s Law and having the five values from <em>Herschel</em>, we can make an adjustment of the observations to obtain the temperature and density of the molecular cloud being observed.</p>
<div id="fig-planck" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/ley-de-planck.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Planck's Law and observational coverage of *Herschel*."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;1: Black body radiation (Planck’s law) as a function of wavelength, in microns. This is the typical emission pattern of molecular clouds. The lines show the emission of clouds at 10, 20, 30, and 50 degrees Kelvin (-263, -253, -243, -223 degrees Celsius respectively). The maximum of emission is determined mainly by temperature, while the normalization (vertical displacement of the function) is influenced by density. The vertical bands show the wavelengths observed by Herschel (100, 160, 250, 350, 500 microns from left to right). The two red bands are the bands with calibration problems that we are going to solve in this work.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="the-calibration-problems-of-herschel-and-the-consequences-for-research" class="level1">
<h1>The Calibration Problems of <em>Herschel</em> and the Consequences for Research</h1>
<p>The challenge we face is the following: <em>Herschel</em>’s observations at 100 and 160 microns have not been properly calibrated. Poor calibration of instruments inevitably leads to erroneous or less precise measurements. If we aim to measure the gas density in molecular clouds to discern whether gravity or turbulence induces the gravitational collapse process that leads to star formation, we need to improve this instrumental calibration. The fact is that the observational difference predicted by models to discern between turbulence and gravity is so subtle that the necessary observations must be extremely precise. The objective of this work is to improve the calibration of the instruments and generate the most accurate temperature and density maps ever obtained of the entire galactic plane.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The definition of the sky level or zero level of the emission observed by <em>Herschel</em> at 100 and 160 microns is not well defined, generating inaccuracies in the measurements. The goal of this work is to combine the observations of <em>Herschel</em> and <em>Planck</em> to improve the zero-level calibration, thus obtaining more precise maps of temperature and density of the galactic molecular clouds. This will help to improve our understanding of which process is responsible for inducing star formation activity.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The calibration of these bands was originally carried out under the assumption that the sky emits uniformly across the entire field of view. This is definitely false. To put it mildly, it might be called an oversimplification. In regions of high emission due to dust, such as the galactic plane, the variation in emission is so significant that assuming a constant sky background results in a calibration as accurate as throwing three twenty-sided dice and trying to predict their exact outcomes. Without accurate calibration, it’s impossible to measure precise densities or temperatures of molecular clouds, which consequently means that it is not possible to determine which physical processes are acting in star formation. Calibration errors, although they may be small for the most compact objects (small in image extension), become huge and unpredictable on a large scale, in the more diffuse areas of the molecular clouds. This exacerbates our problem, as it is in these large-scale diffuse areas where most of the mass of molecular clouds is found. These are also the areas that show the least star formation activity and are therefore the most interesting to study in order to discern which processes cause a diffuse area to become dense and consequently form stars.</p>
</section>
<section id="combining-data-from-herschel-and-planck-for-more-accurate-temperature-and-density-maps" class="level1">
<h1>Combining Data from <em>Herschel</em> and <em>Planck</em> for More Accurate Temperature and Density Maps</h1>
<p>In this work, we take advantage of the launch of another space observatory that, although intended for a completely different mission (measuring the echo of the Big Bang), provides us with the necessary tools to recalibrate Herschel’s observations. The <em>Planck</em> observatory generated large-scale, full-sky observations in its search for the <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Radiaci%C3%B3n_de_fondo_de_microondas">cosmic microwave background</a>. To achieve its goal, <em>Planck</em> had a <em>small obstacle</em>. Measuring the cosmic background radiation means knowing what’s behind our own Galaxy: the Milky Way. Therefore, <em>Planck</em> had to subtract the emission of our Galaxy, as it blocks the cosmic background radiation being between it and us. As a result, <em>Planck</em> generated very precise maps of the sky’s density and temperature, although at higher angular resolutions than those of <em>Herschel</em>. We can use these maps to recalibrate Herschel’s images.</p>
<p>In this case, <em>Planck</em> provides us with the temperature and density of each point in the Milky Way. We take this information and perform a reverse engineering of the process shown in Figura&nbsp;1. Using the temperature and density of the gas obtained at each point in the Milky Way with the <em>Planck</em> telescope, we can calculate the theoretical emission of each point in the Galaxy using Planck’s Law.<font color="#df6919"><strong>(Unfortunately, we have to use the name Planck to mention two different objects. Note that Planck’s Law is the mathematical function of molecular clouds’ emission, while Planck in italics refers to the telescope.)</strong></font> Now, knowing the theoretical emission of each point in the galaxy and also knowing the exact sensitivity of <em>Herschel</em> to each wavelength, we can obtain simulated images of what the <em>Planck</em> telescope would see if it had the same instruments as the <em>Herschel</em> telescope. In this case, we also know that <em>Planck</em>’s calibration is very precise, as this is a key requirement for the success of the <em>Planck</em> mission. Ultimately, we can use <em>Planck</em>’s observations to correct <em>Herschel</em>’s large-scale calibration problems, thus obtaining the best existing map of density and temperature of the Milky Way.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Importante
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The reader may wonder: if <em>Planck</em> already has the maps of density and temperature… Why not just use them and save ourselves all this arduous work? The answer is that <em>Planck</em> is a much smaller telescope than <em>Herschel</em>. This translates to <em>Planck</em> having significant myopia compared to <em>Herschel</em>. In other words, <em>Herschel</em>’s observations are much sharper and reveal subtler details than those of <em>Planck</em>. It’s as if <em>Herschel</em> uses glasses to correct the myopia of <em>Planck</em>. Specifically, at 100 and 160 microns <em>Herschel</em> can see details 12 and 17 times smaller, respectively, than <em>Planck</em>. This can be clearly observed in Figura&nbsp;2, Figura&nbsp;3, and Figura&nbsp;4. This is especially important, as it is in those small details revealed by <em>Herschel</em> where we must look for the answers to open questions about the star formation process.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="fig-planck-orion" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/planck-orion-complex.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Orion Map obtained by *Planck*."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;2: Observations of the Orion molecular complex by the <em>Planck</em> telescope. The lines correspond to the polarization of light. (Credit: <a href="https://sci.esa.int/web/planck/-/55911-polarised-emission-from-orion-annotated">ESA and the Planck Collaboration</a>)</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-panel">
<div class="quarto-layout-row quarto-layout-valign-top">
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-herschel-orion-a" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/herschel-orion-a.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Orion A Map obtained by *Herschel*."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;3: Observations of the Orion A molecular cloud (the Great Orion Nebula) by the <em>Herschel</em> telescope. Greater detail is clearly observed compared to the observations of <em>Planck</em> in Figura&nbsp;2. <a href="https://sci.esa.int/web/herschel/-/59534-herschel-s-view-of-orion-b">Copyright: ESA/Herschel/NASA/JPL-Caltech, CC BY-SA 3.0 IGO; Acknowledgement: R. Hurt (JPL-Caltech)</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
<div class="quarto-layout-cell" style="flex-basis: 50.0%;justify-content: center;">
<div id="fig-herschel-orion-b" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/herschel-orion-b.jpg" class="img-fluid figure-img" alt="Orion B Map obtained by *Herschel*."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;4: Observations of the Orion B molecular cloud (the Great Orion Nebula) by the <em>Herschel</em> telescope. Greater detail is clearly observed compared to the observations of <em>Planck</em> in Figura&nbsp;2. Copyright: <a href="https://www.esa.int/ESA_Multimedia/Images/2013/08/Orion_A">ESA/Herschel/Ph. André, D. Polychroni, A. Roy, V. Könyves, N. Schneider for the Gould Belt survey Key Programme.</a></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</div>
</div>
</div>
<p>Due to the very specialized and intense technical explanation required for this process, we do not delve deeper into this post, referring the reader to <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2017">(Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2017)</span> for more information. As a brief summary, we can say that the technique used follows a series of steps:</p>
<ol type="1">
<li><p>Obtain simulated emission maps of how <em>Planck</em> would observe using the same instruments as <em>Herschel</em>.</p></li>
<li><p>Joint calibration of the data from <em>Herschel</em> and <em>Planck</em>. Ensure that both are on the same scale.</p></li>
<li><p>Combine the images of <em>Herschel</em> and <em>Planck</em> in the Fourier space.</p></li>
</ol>
<p>The results obtained with this technique have proven to be truly spectacular. To demonstrate their validity, we first applied the method to a simulated molecular cloud, of which we could know exactly its real density and temperatures. After validating the method, we applied it to two test regions: Orion and Perseus. The latter can be seen in Figura&nbsp;5. The application of our method has improved the estimation of masses observed by <em>Herschel</em> in Perseus by values of up to 30%. In general, our method is capable of correcting the masses (equivalent to densities in the methods used) of molecular clouds by factors varying from 1 to 100. This achievement is truly impressive and is currently being applied to the entirety of observations of the Milky Way carried out by <em>Herschel</em>. Once completed, we will have achieved the most accurate map of temperature and density of molecular clouds in the Milky Way to date. Thanks to this work, we finally hope to contribute to the answer to the enigma of turbulence or gravity as the main cause of star formation.</p>
<div id="fig-results" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/results_herschel_planck.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Results of combining observations from the *Planck* and *Herschel* telescopes."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;5: Left: Density map of a region in the Perseus molecular cloud using our innovative calibration technique for Herschel observations. Right: Comparison of the density obtained by our new method and the density of the official Herschel data. White areas show regions where both methods are equal (mainly, and as expected, the more compact and dense areas). Blue areas indicate regions where previous Herschel maps overestimated densities. Red areas show regions where Herschel underestimated densities before our new calibration.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Referencias</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_2017" class="csl-entry">
Abreu-Vicente, J., A. Stutz, Th. Henning, E. Keto, J. Ballesteros-Paredes, y T. Robitaille. 2017. <span>«Fourier-space combination of Planck and Herschel images»</span>. <em>Astronomy <span>&amp;</span> Astrophysics</em> 604 (agosto): A65. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201628891">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201628891</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_blog_atlastgal" class="csl-entry">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>«Revelando el causante de la formación estelar»</span>. 31 de octubre de 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-10-31-revelando-causa-formacion-estelar/">https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-10-31-revelando-causa-formacion-estelar/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Li_2014" class="csl-entry">
Li, Shule, Adam Frank, y Eric G. Blackman. 2014. <span>«Triggered star formation and its consequences»</span>. <em>Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society</em> 444 (3): 2884-92. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stu1571">https://doi.org/10.1093/mnras/stu1571</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Notas</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>The visible light range is the light emitted at frequencies sensitive to our eyes. For more information about the electromagnetic spectrum visit <a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Espectro_electromagn%C3%A9tico">WikiPedia</a>↩︎</p></li>
<li id="fn2"><p>Although not mentioned in these works, there is a third process believed to induce the onset of the star formation process. This is the compression of molecular clouds by radiation from massive stars or supernova explosions <span class="citation" data-cites="Li_2014">(Li, Frank, y Blackman 2014)</span>.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Cómo citar</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{jorge abreu-vicente2023,
  author = {Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr.},
  title = {Goolgles for *Planck* and *Herschel*. Enhanced calibration of
    *Herschel* and *Planck* Data in the Galactic plane},
  date = {2023-11-01},
  url = {https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/},
  langid = {es}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">Por favor, cita este trabajo como:</div><div id="ref-jorge abreu-vicente2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>“Goolgles for *Planck* and
*Herschel*. Enhanced calibration of *Herschel* and *Planck* Data in the
Galactic plane.”</span> November 1, 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/">https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Science</category>
  <category>Astronomy</category>
  <category>Star Formation</category>
  <category>PhD Thesis</category>
  <guid>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Tue, 31 Oct 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-11-01-best-fir-view-milky-way/herschel-main-pic.jpg" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"/>
</item>
<item>
  <title>Deciphering the evolutionary journey of molecular clouds</title>
  <dc:creator>Dr. Jorge Abreu-Vicente</dc:creator>
  <link>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/index.html</link>
  <description><![CDATA[ 




<p>Based on <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2015">(Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2015)</span>. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/es/posts/2023-10-31-revelando-causa-formacion-estelar/">Versión del post en español 🇪🇸</a></p>
<section id="the-relationship-between-star-formation-and-density-in-molecular-clouds" class="level1">
<h1>The relationship between star formation and density in molecular clouds</h1>
<p>Stars are born in the coldest and densest regions of molecular clouds, which are in turn the predominant structure filling the space between stars (the interstellar medium). This is an empirical fact, confirmed by numerous studies extending over decades-long research.</p>
<p>Molecular clouds produce stars which, in turn, modify the material they were created from to send it back into the interstellar medium, thus forming new stars by recycling the dead-stellar material. For this reason, <font color="#df6919"><strong>molecular clouds play a crucial role in galactic evolution</strong></font>. Consequently, the study of the evolution of molecular clouds is of great interest to the scientific community.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-tip callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Tip
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Not only are stars formed from recycled material of previous generations. With the only possible exception of some of our building Hydrogen atoms, all the atoms of all the matter you see on Earth (including you and me) have at some point in the history of the Universe been inside a star. Later, this tiny wanderers found themselves in the vast Cosmic void, at temperatures below 200 degrees Celsius in the molecular cloud where our Sun was formed.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>The internal structure of molecular clouds can be used to infer the physical processes acting upon them <span class="citation" data-cites="Hennebelle_2012">(Hennebelle y Falgarone 2012)</span>. Observations show that molecular clouds consist of a series of dense cores, usually wrapped in filamentary structures of slightly lower density <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2016">Jorge Abreu-Vicente (2023)</span>. The cores and filaments are surrounded by a more diffuse (less dense) material that dominates the large scale extension of molecular clouds. The cores are the sites where star formation occurs. They are about half a light-year in size, with masses ranging from 0.1 to 1000 times that of the Sun and temperatures around -250 to -260 degrees Celsius.</p>
</section>
<section id="why-do-we-need-a-systematic-study-of-molecular-clouds-in-the-galactic-plane" class="level1">
<h1>Why do we need a systematic study of molecular clouds in the Galactic plane?</h1>
<p>The main differences between these cores, filaments, and diffuse material are their densities (higher in cores and lower in diffuse areas) and their temperatures, which inversely increase with decreasing density. The density distribution of these elements and of molecular clouds as a whole can therefore be used to study the physical processes acting on them, as well as their relative importance. In the work presented in this post, we conduct the first systematic study of density distributions in molecular clouds across the Milky Way.</p>
<p>Prior to this work, only the density distributions of molecular clouds in the solar neighborhood (a circle about 3000 light-years in diameter with the Sun at its center) had been thoroughly studied <span class="citation" data-cites="jouni09">Kainulainen y Tan (2013)</span>. The reasons are mainly technical limitations in the methods of measuring density <span class="citation" data-cites="Abreu_Vicente_2015">(for more details, Abreu-Vicente et&nbsp;al. 2015)</span>. The problem with <font color="#df6919"><strong>molecular clouds in the solar neighborhood is that they are not representative of the molecular clouds typically found in the Milky Way</strong></font>. Consequently, the findings of Solar Neighborhood molecular clouds can’t be accepted as generic results without further extended studies. For context, the molecular clouds in our vicinity form very few stars, mainly of low mass, and have masses of about 1000 times that of the Sun. The average molecular cloud in our Galaxy has high star-forming activity of both, low- and high-mass stars, and they have masses between 10^5 and 10^6 solar masses.</p>
<p>Hence, in this work we aim to obtain the first systematic study of the relationship between density distribution and star formation in molecular clouds at Galactic scales. In this way, we could finally extrapolate the results to a more general scenario. With these results, we will be able to test the current theoretical paradigms about the processes that trigger star formation. The most specific scenarios are: gravity, turbulence, and to a lesser extent, magnetic fields.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Importante
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>We note that other scenarios, such as star-formation activity triggered by compression of nearby massive stars and supernova explosions, have been also suggested. However, our work is not intended to share light in these two processes.</p>
</div>
</div>
<p>Previous works show that the density distribution in molecular clouds with and without star formation activity are fundamentally different <span class="citation" data-cites="jouni09">Schneider et&nbsp;al. (2013)</span>. Molecular clouds with star formation show higher amounts of material concentrated in dense areas. This can be seen in Figura&nbsp;1. Clouds without active star formation (quiescent, in the left panel) have a density distribution in the form of a log-normal function, while active clouds, like Taurus in the right panel, show a clear excess of material above the log-normal line (solid) in the right side of the graph representing dense regions.</p>
<p>The interesting aspect of these results lies in the analytical form of the functions. Theoretical simulations show that a molecular cloud in which gas turbulence is the main physical process evolves in such a way that its density distribution follows a log-normal function <span class="citation" data-cites="vs94">Lombardi, Alves, y Lada (2015)</span>. Conversely, molecular clouds dominated by gravity have an exponential distribution, similar to the “straight line” shown by Taurus at high densities. These results suggest that, at least in clouds in the Solar Neighborhood: turbulence dominates the evolution of molecular clouds without star formation, while gravity is the dominant process in clouds with star formation.</p>
<div id="fig-jouni" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/pdfs-jouni.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Density distribution of two molecular clouds in the solar neighborhood."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;1: Density distribution of two molecular clouds in the Solar Neighborhood. On the left, Lupus without active star formation and on the right Taurus, with active star formation. The density distribution of Lupus follows a log-normal function (solid line), while that of Taurus represents a clear deviation in excess of this function. Source: <span class="citation" data-cites="jouni09">(Kainulainen et&nbsp;al. 2009)</span></figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
</section>
<section id="observing-molecular-clouds-in-different-evolutionary-stages-reveals-the-dominant-physical-processes-in-action" class="level1">
<h1>Observing molecular clouds in different evolutionary stages reveals the dominant Physical processes in action</h1>
<p>In this work, we define three types of molecular clouds based on their star formation activity: quiescent clouds (without star formation), star-forming clouds, and HII regions. The latter are clouds in which star formation has taken place during the last few million years. In these, the new stars, through their ultraviolet radiation, have ionized and completely reshaped their parent clouds. Quiescent clouds reveal themselves as dark patches against the NIR background emission of the Galactic plane. Star-forming clouds are a mix between the other two evolutionary stages, appearing as dark patches with small bright NIR spots. Examples of the three stages are shown in Figura&nbsp;2.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Importante
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>It is important to note that the choice of molecular cloud types in this work is justified by their logical (although not observationally confirmed, as it would require at least a million years of waiting) evolutionary sequence: clouds are first in a quiescent state, then begin to form stars, until massive stars form and with their early-stage radiation dissolve the molecular cloud. The article discusses in depth the possible explanations and exceptions to this evolutionary sequence.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div id="fig-evol-stages" class="quarto-figure quarto-figure-center anchored">
<figure class="figure">
<p><img src="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/gmcs-evolved.png" class="img-fluid figure-img" style="width:100.0%" alt="Density distribution of two molecular clouds in the solar neighborhood."></p>
<figcaption class="figure-caption">Figura&nbsp;2: Top left, example of a molecular cloud without star formation activity (quiescent). Below, a molecular cloud hosting star-forming activity (red point-sources on the dark background that is the molecular cloud). Top right shows an HII region. Source: Spitzer Space Telescope.</figcaption>
</figure>
</div>
<p>The results of our work show that Galactic molecular clouds exhibit a density distribution similar to those in the solar neighborhood, depending on their star formation activity. Quiescent clouds follow a log-normal function. Star-forming clouds show an excess of gas in dense regions compared to the log-normal. Finally, HII regions are dominated almost entirely by an exponential component.</p>
<p>Following this result, the question that came to mind was the following: Let’s assume that our three types of clouds show a sequential evolutionary process. In other words, every molecular cloud will evolve from quiescent to HII<sup>1</sup>, passing through the intermediate state. And the results show a gradual increase in dense gas in this sequence. Could we use the amount of dense gas in a molecular cloud to determine its age based on its density distribution?</p>
<p>And the answer turned out to be yes. Simulations show that in a gravity-dominated cloud, the point at which its density distribution deviates from the log-normal function is directly related to the age of the cloud <span class="citation" data-cites="girich14">(Girichidis et&nbsp;al. 2014)</span>. Or at least the age since gravity began to dominate certain regions of the cloud. After rigorous calculations, we concluded that the average age of our quiescent clouds is about 10^5 years, star-forming clouds have an average age of half a million years, and HII regions would have an average age of about 2 million years. These values are remarkably similar to estimates made with completely independent methods for the ages of star-forming cores, protostars, and massive stars, which are the main elements of our three regions. Therefore, <font color="#df6919"><strong>we suggest that there is a relationship between star formation, density distribution, and the evolution of molecular clouds, and that this is seen in clouds scattered throughout the Galactic plane</strong></font>.</p>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Importante
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>Our work suggests the following theoretical framework for the evolution of molecular clouds and star formation: in their first 10^5 years, molecular clouds are in a state dominated by turbulence. At a certain point, turbulence will generate areas of gas with higher density than their surroundings. These regions will become self-gravitating and begin the collapse towards star formation, while the rest of the cloud continues in a state dominated by turbulence. This process will continue and gradually more and more self-gravitating areas will be generated. Eventually, massive stars will be formed that will eventually dissolve their parent cloud with their strong UV radiation. We see that turbulence and gravity take turns during the life of a molecular cloud. However, it is ultimately gravity that causes star formation.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout callout-style-default callout-important callout-titled">
<div class="callout-header d-flex align-content-center">
<div class="callout-icon-container">
<i class="callout-icon"></i>
</div>
<div class="callout-title-container flex-fill">
Importante
</div>
</div>
<div class="callout-body-container callout-body">
<p>The radiation pressure by massive stars in HII regions might be a non-neglectable contributor to the star formation in the later stage. However, we can not put it into numbers with the techniques used in the present study. This gap should be filled in future studies.</p>
</div>
</div>



</section>


<div id="quarto-appendix" class="default"><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Referencias</h2><div id="refs" class="references csl-bib-body hanging-indent">
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_2015" class="csl-entry">
Abreu-Vicente, J., J. Kainulainen, A. Stutz, Th. Henning, y H. Beuther. 2015. <span>«Relationship between the column density distribution and evolutionary class of molecular clouds as viewed by ATLASGAL»</span>. <em>Astronomy <span>&amp;</span> Astrophysics</em> 581 (septiembre): A74. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201424959">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201424959</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_2016" class="csl-entry">
Abreu-Vicente, J., S. Ragan, J. Kainulainen, Th. Henning, H. Beuther, y K. Johnston. 2016. <span>«Giant molecular filaments in the Milky Way»</span>. <em>Astronomy <span>&amp;</span> Astrophysics</em> 590 (mayo): A131. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201527674">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201527674</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-federrath13" class="csl-entry">
Federrath, Christoph, y Ralf S. Klessen. 2013. <span>«<span>On the Star Formation Efficiency of Turbulent Magnetized Clouds</span>»</span> 763 (1): 51. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/763/1/51">https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/763/1/51</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-girich14" class="csl-entry">
Girichidis, Philipp, Lukas Konstandin, Anthony P. Whitworth, y Ralf S. Klessen. 2014. <span>«<span>On the Evolution of the Density Probability Density Function in Strongly Self-gravitating Systems</span>»</span> 781 (2): 91. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/781/2/91">https://doi.org/10.1088/0004-637X/781/2/91</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Hennebelle_2012" class="csl-entry">
Hennebelle, Patrick, y Edith Falgarone. 2012. <span>«Turbulent molecular clouds»</span>. <em>The Astronomy and Astrophysics Review</em> 20 (1). <a href="https://doi.org/10.1007/s00159-012-0055-y">https://doi.org/10.1007/s00159-012-0055-y</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Abreu_Vicente_blog_filaments" class="csl-entry">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>«Paleontología Galáctica: desenterramos una tela de araña galáctica»</span>. 2 de noviembre de 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-11-02-filamentos-moleculares-gigantes/">https://drAbreu.github.io/es/posts/2023-11-02-filamentos-moleculares-gigantes/</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-jouni09" class="csl-entry">
Kainulainen, J., H. Beuther, T. Henning, y R. Plume. 2009. <span>«<span>Probing the evolution of molecular cloud structure. From quiescence to birth</span>»</span> 508 (3): L35-38. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/200913605">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/200913605</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kainulainen_2013" class="csl-entry">
Kainulainen, J., C. Federrath, y T. Henning. 2013. <span>«Connection between dense gas mass fraction, turbulence driving, and star formation efficiency of molecular clouds»</span>. <em>Astronomy <span>&amp;</span> Astrophysics</em> 553 (mayo): L8. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201321431">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201321431</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Kainulainen_2013_b" class="csl-entry">
Kainulainen, J., y J. C. Tan. 2013. <span>«<span>High-dynamic-range extinction mapping of infrared dark clouds. Dependence of density variance with sonic Mach number in molecular clouds</span>»</span> 549 (enero): A53. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201219526">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201219526</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-lomb15" class="csl-entry">
Lombardi, Marco, João Alves, y Charles J. Lada. 2015. <span>«<span>Molecular clouds have power-law probability distribution functions</span>»</span> 576 (abril): L1. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201525650">https://doi.org/10.1051/0004-6361/201525650</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Schneider_2013" class="csl-entry">
Schneider, N., Ph. André, V. Koenyves, S. Bontemps, F. Motte, C. Federrath, D. Ward-Thompson, et&nbsp;al. 2013. <span>«What determines the density structure of molecular clouds ? A case study of Orion B with Herschel»</span>. <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em> 766 (2): L17. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1088/2041-8205/766/2/l17">https://doi.org/10.1088/2041-8205/766/2/l17</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-vs94" class="csl-entry">
Vazquez-Semadeni, Enrique. 1994. <span>«<span>Hierarchical Structure in Nearly Pressureless Flows as a Consequence of Self-similar Statistics</span>»</span> 423 (marzo): 681. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/173847">https://doi.org/10.1086/173847</a>.
</div>
<div id="ref-Vazquez_Semadeni_2001" class="csl-entry">
Vazquez-Semadeni, Enrique, y Nieves Garcia. 2001. <span>«The Probability Distribution Function of Column Density in Molecular Clouds»</span>. <em>The Astrophysical Journal</em> 557 (2): 727-35. <a href="https://doi.org/10.1086/321688">https://doi.org/10.1086/321688</a>.
</div>
</div></section><section id="footnotes" class="footnotes footnotes-end-of-document"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Notas</h2>

<ol>
<li id="fn1"><p>Low mass star-forming clouds such as those in the Solar Neighborhood might never have stars massive enough to generate HII regions.↩︎</p></li>
</ol>
</section><section class="quarto-appendix-contents"><h2 class="anchored quarto-appendix-heading">Cómo citar</h2><div><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">BibTeX</div><pre class="sourceCode code-with-copy quarto-appendix-bibtex"><code class="sourceCode bibtex">@online{jorge abreu-vicente2023,
  author = {Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr.},
  title = {Deciphering the evolutionary journey of molecular clouds},
  date = {2023-10-31},
  url = {https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/},
  langid = {es}
}
</code></pre><div class="quarto-appendix-secondary-label">Por favor, cita este trabajo como:</div><div id="ref-jorge abreu-vicente2023" class="csl-entry quarto-appendix-citeas">
Jorge Abreu-Vicente, Dr. 2023. <span>“Deciphering the evolutionary
journey of molecular clouds.”</span> October 31, 2023. <a href="https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/">https://drAbreu.github.io/web/en/posts/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/</a>.
</div></div></section></div> ]]></description>
  <category>Science</category>
  <category>Astronomy</category>
  <category>Star Formation</category>
  <category>PhD Thesis</category>
  <guid>https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/index.html</guid>
  <pubDate>Mon, 30 Oct 2023 23:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
  <media:content url="https://drabreu.github.io/web/en/projects/2023-10-31-revealing-star-forming-trigger/orion-sf.png" medium="image" type="image/png" height="134" width="144"/>
</item>
</channel>
</rss>
